all right
uh we're gonna do a question and answer
and if anybody has
questions Tim is going to choose so the
pressure's off of me
thank you my question is if we listen to
the same teaching and listen to our
teacher over and over again multiple
lifetimes how do we change our minds and
thoughts and actions okay good
uh
the question was if we listened to our
teacher over and over again especially
in multiple lifetimes
then how do we actually change our
thoughts and actions and there's a thing
called tiptoe
which is my one of my teachers favorite
expressions
means
his example was
if a kid acts up he was a school teacher
in the refugee camp so he he got stuck
with the elementary school
and uh he wrote the textbooks for the
elementary schools and
and so he said there's a kind of a bad
kid when you correct them
they don't improve and then you correct
them again and then they correct them
again and then tap them means
they get used to correct correction from
my teacher was hitting you with Amala on
the head uh
hitting you with a rosary on that and
then he said some kids they just get
to where they don't mind the Rosemary on
the head anymore and they just get used
to it
he he would say that's a great Danger
uh like your teacher is trying to
correct you and you get used to the
correction and then you learn to live
with the correction and not correct
yourself
and uh so there is such a thing as
chapter
and uh
I think for me when I went this was a
famous conversation with my teacher and
I was fortunate
to live with my teacher for 25 years
and so that was a unique
training school I was the only Foreigner
who survived in his
residence
and many many were sent away in
other bad things so uh
so I remember I I went to him I asked
him this question I asked him almost all
the questions you can think of
and he said
I said what if what if you keep
correcting me
and I get used to the correction and I
don't correct myself and then you keep
repeating the same correction and then I
don't change and then I get immune to
your corrections to where I don't hear
them anymore
and he said oh
that's not a problem and I'm like what
do you mean it's not a promises
suffering
I'm like what he said the world will
crush you the world will bring you new
problems you know the world will
give you some terrible things will
happen to you and then you'll come and
listen to me you know so I'm like okay
he says you don't have to do anything
just be alive
in the world will bring you new problems
and then you'll come back to me and then
you'll listen you know you know so
so you don't have to do anything
just live
and uh life will life itself will remind
you that that you have to listen to your
teacher and and I'm
it's it's not facetious I'm not just
saying it as a joke or something it's
really true
so but the the
trick is to stay in contact or
contactable
with your teachers so you know if you
don't you there's times when you kind of
uh spend time away from your teacher
but always have that option set up
that you can get in touch with your
teacher or you can
get back to them and ask them for their
help like that so don't don't burn the
bridge
keep the keep the option open
to get help from them when you
when life will
remind you you don't you
if you're really smart you can
anticipate what life's gonna do but very
few people can do that
you can guest by observing other people
getting old
or you know dying or getting cancer you
can guess that it's going to happen to
you so if you're really intelligent
you can work ahead of the game
and and be in touch with your teacher
but if you're just a normal person you
could wait till you get cancer and then
you
be in touch with your teacher so when
the time comes you can you can get help
okay
so it's kind of like just be alive and
think so
the connection will be remade when it
when you need it
and that's happened in my life I've
had many many students over the course
of my life and
and they come back they have a challenge
and they come they get sick or something
happens and they
they come back and that's okay and then
we reconnect and and I wake up all the
old teachings and it's fine
it works out so
Mr team
[Music]
you got me
this is a question that came online
actually last week on our Facebook page
a friend of ours who is her mother got
really sick during covid
and wasn't able to fly to Mexico as she
was passing away even though her mom had
asked her to be able to do so
and it turned out that her mother passed
away before she was able able to go and
wasn't able to be there with her and
it's brought her a lot of deep grief
and she wanted to know how she could
think about this and what advice might
you have
even though she wasn't able to be there
that maybe that could help her as her
mother had transitioned yeah cool uh
so this happens to to many of us and
and it happened to me
and I took care of my real mom
as she was dying and uh actually my
teacher asked
advised me to bring her to take
teachings in in the Himalayas and she
came
she was already uh
very very ill with cancer in her brain
and she came for I think two two months
or three months
and listen to teachings and but I I
couldn't be there when she died so I
know the question
and um
what I would say
there's a practice that my teacher
taught me
people used to come to him
and say my my mom passed away or they
would ask questions like this
and I remember
our relationship got to where I asked
him so many questions
that he got tired of being asked
questions
and he decided he would take his meals
in his room alone
and
so then I would go up and serve the meal
and trying to get sit down and ask a
question and then
and then it got really bad and the only
time I could get a question was
traveling with him
like if we were in the car together
and then he'd pretend he was asleep
[Music]
but uh we were on a flight to India
and uh so that's a 12 hours either
either way sometimes 20 hours in
in the plane and
so I and he was next to me stuck
and um he couldn't pretend to sleep for
12 hours
and I asked him
if he had some advice for situations
like this and he gave me a long he said
take take a note you know he would say
take a note and he gave me a long
teaching it was like three four hours
about what to do in a situation like
this and it was very beautiful
what he said was very beautiful
and said
and by the way sugang's book also uh the
new the new new book
it has a nice section on Bardo on the
Bargo there's a appendix on the border
and
during the Bardo during the time between
death and rebirth
uh those beings have special powers
and they can uh and and
in segang's book we translated that
section
so it's not some kind of
um there's a book called Book of the
Dead or something like that
which is not accepted by
uh by by the people who understand the
partner they
that book is um what do you call it
it's just somebody made up stuff in
there so I would not advise you to use
that or read it I had a friend who
tried to use it and spent time in a
mental hospital
so I don't think it's my teacher said
don't use that book but there are in the
abhi Dharma there are good Solid 2 000
year old teaching son what happens to
you
after you die
and
my teacher taught that he taught it from
the ugly Dharma in
they say that a Bardo Bean has special
powers
and they can understand all languages
25 for the yoga Sutra line about that
never mind
they can speak they can understand all
languages all human languages they can
understand
so they have a special Karma
and if you study uh the Bardo
beings habits
their mental state their different
powers from the RB Dharma kosher
you can
it's real they really can understand uh
when you speak
to them and I had a dream like that my
college roommate died
and um
I was helping his wife and their two
kids and
um
he died suddenly and I had a dream about
him and he was
in the bottle and he was behind a glass
and he was at his house
and he was watching his wife and their
two kids eat breakfast and he was trying
to talk to them
and they couldn't
hear him but he could hear them
and he was banging on the glass
uh because he was upset
because he didn't know he was dead uh
and they were ignoring him and uh and
it's like that so they can
hear their family members and they can
understand uh when you speak
so my teacher encouraged people
speak to their relatives
who passed away
and uh and he made a whole practice
about it and it's very beautiful in
in friends who've been doing it for 20
years
30 years I've I've taught this 20 years
ago
in so you can
now when you're alone in a room
uh you can do it I like to go to a park
or something and sit on a park bench
probably people think I'm an odd old man
talking to himself
but I'll go to a park and sit on a bench
and talk to my mom
or something like that and they can hear
you
and they can understand you so uh
it's nice if you want to help them
if so what I mean is it's probably more
useful for your mom
if you talk to them while they're after
they've died than it is to be there when
they die
uh as the person is dying
there's very little they can you can do
for them they cannot
think straight they cannot
um it's too frightening and their sense
organs are breaking down that's not the
time to talk to somebody okay
uh they can understand more they can
hear more afterwards
afterwards so I wouldn't be so worried
that you weren't there
at the moment that a person that your
mom passed away and it's not
that crucial it's helpful but it's not
that crucial you can do a lot more good
afterwards
and keep talking to them keep
encouraging them
uh what What's a nice practice what my
teacher
asked me to do was keep a list of things
my mom had done for me
and nice things she had done for me
and then thank her and talk to her
and he said that's a really cool idea
because it makes you more grateful
and it reminds her
the best things she has done in her life
and then we call box Tampa
uh
which is the eighth and Ninth limbs
of the 12 lengths of the Wheel of Life
which means uh
if your mom can if you talk to your mom
about nice things they did for you
then she will remember
and that will wake up those seats
seeds that she has in her mind
from having helped you
when you remind her or talk to her about
you know I remember when you took me to
the surf shop and bought me the
impossibly expensive
five foot eleven
blue surfboard for 85 and it was a lot
of money for us at the time
and I remember when you did that and and
then you know talk to them about things
they did for you
and that's a lot more powerful so I I
would say it's not a
you know and that you can do
indefinitely you can do it for 20 years
it doesn't matter and the list
if you keep a little Journal
about nice nice things they did for you
uh it gets longer and longer in my
journal was 85 pages
stuff that she had done for me and um
so it's a great practice
It's a Wonderful practice and you can
keep doing it so I think it's a lot more
important to do that than to be there at
the moment that they path
you know
it's a lot it's a lot more useful for
her and for you if you do this practice
of talking to her
and reminding her about cool stuff she
did
and that list will just keep getting
longer and longer
one more Timothy
very cool thank you for that
so this question kind of plays off of
Anna Lee's question Eli's question from
yesterday
so the question is when we think about
emptiness or we're thinking more about
the
the gotcha the thing that's not there
and we're doing this practice of
canceling everything that's not there
and then the thing that arises is the
thing that is there
the question really is what is the seed
this the question is what is the seed
for the mental picture at this time
specifically related to emptiness
so if you're having a direct perception
of emptiness you've canceled everything
that's not emptiness
emptiness is something that's not there
that you thought was there what is that
suit
what is the mental picture that arises
in
yeah it's good that's a good question
a deep question
so um
the direct perception to Emptiness is
divided into two parts
in
Sanskrit
balanced meditation balance between what
for fifty dollars
Chloe
Thomas and agitation good between
dullness and agitation yeah
did I say five dollars I don't remember
uh
so yes she means during the actual
direct perception
you are uh focusing on the absence of an
impossible thing
so you are directly perceiving
the fact that nothing is not coming from
you okay
double negative
so during that time
you cannot have any other perceptions
not possible what's the most frustrating
perception you cannot have at that
moment
I did it yeah okay yeah you cannot say I
did it because I is not emptiness
uh did it is not emptiness uh it is not
well
so uh
so then
but there's something happens in the
direct perception of emptiness
the power
of the absence
of anything that doesn't come from you
that
absence has a specific power
okay the the fact
that nothing's not coming from you okay
that fact which is the highest thing in
the universe
okay now that is the highest thing in
if you if you want to have a God that's
God
okay by the way someone reminded me it's
not only Easter it's Passover and
Ramadan so uh
uh you know congratulations to everybody
it's also Easter break for Joe and the
other college students um
just kidding so
the extreme power of seeing highest
reality
does something in the following means
the aftermath okay so like the Afterglow
and and you could talk about it in yoga
terms in Prana terms Chi that for the
first time
all of your Prana has entered the
central Channel all the tea is in the
Jung mind
and uh and that for the first time and
when you come down
out of the direct perception in the 20
minutes or so
uh the chi is still there
uh in unprecedented quantity in the
central Channel It's Not Gonna Leave the
central Channel
the moment you come out of shamita
so it stays there for about 24 hours
and because of that you have
extraordinary normal perceptions
which are not emptiness
and those are called the
16 aspects of the Aria for for higher
Truth For Audio truth and they include
for example seeing directly the day of
your death
so nobody really believes they're gonna
die except an Arya
because Anaya has seen it directly
they have seen for an Arya they don't
say die they say uh
on the day that gravity wins the contest
okay like
you are a weird animal that walks
upright
thinking about it yesterday I went for a
long walk and uh
all the animal paths here are
frustrating because they go under trees
and under bushes animals are are only
this high
so you can't really follow the animal
path here because they go under
everything you see what I mean human
beings are one of the few creatures that
compete with gravity in their whole life
you know they struggle to learn to walk
out to to stand up
unnaturally vertically
and then uh sooner or later that contest
is won by gravity and an Arya has seen
that they have seen directly that they
have their death by the way they've also
seen where they are going afterwards so
they they're kind of like okay
they know what's coming next so and then
of course they have this perception of
uh buddy Taylor and they have actual
body children real body chiller and they
meet every living being and they've gone
through their
dachshund right they've been through
that practice number which of the five
most
exchanging myself and others
number four okay step number four
so they've been through that they know
how to do it they meet every living
being directly
so uh
so the aftermath when The Prana is still
in the central Channel
it's a lot of not direct perceptions of
emptiness they are normal perceptions
they are abnormal but super normal
but they are not the direct perception
of emptiness and the things they see
are positive things and not an absence
of something so it's different right
right so that's the main thing you you
that's the relationship between
an unchanging negative object emptiness
and then all of those 16 aspects of the
four truths for example senior death
seeing where you're headed after that
uh meeting every living being those
those are Fallout you can say Fallout up
from the experience okay and those are
normal perceptions of of changing
objects positive objects okay does that
does that help so the direct perception
of something that's not there
leads to many
subsequent J tote means subsequent uh
perceptions of high changing truth okay
cool
I guess so
that's how I want to cover it okay
we're gonna go back to the text okay
um
I'm really making an attempt to finish
this book before
2080 or something all right uh
means I'm now I'm going to give you the
real thing okay so finally
also is getting down print all right
here's part four
here's how to exchange yourself and
others okay
Samba
[Music]
sampa means learn we finished thinking
about the kyuns
and we finished thinking about the
humans he's making up
a alliteration
yeah
so anyway kin means problems of
trying to
the yeah the useless attempt to take
care of yourself first
and again you can keep doing it as long
as you want it's hopeless
it doesn't work
but if you're okay you wanna
you wanna have a miserable life keep
doing it
you know keep trying take care of
yourself first okay then uh
good qualities do you know just let go
and focus on other people's needs your
needs will get covered automatically
don't worry about it
just
in the habit
of seeing what the people around you
need
and accommodate it it doesn't mean I I
don't buy this sacrifice thing that you
have to sacrifice your happiness
and work on other people's happiness
it's unnatural nobody will do it
okay it just happens to be luckily
that when you focus on what other people
need that's how you that's the happiest
thing you can do
so
so that's lucky it works out that way
you don't have to make a choice between
what you want and what other people want
you just have to get really good at
synthesizing
that too so that you can get everything
you want and they get everything they
want
and that's a happy ending for everybody
okay
all right so somebody okay
now that we've discussed
how hopeless it is to try to take care
of yourself first all the time running d
uh he says you should think about those
four verses
and then he gives the first line of 16
lines and he says everybody knows the
rest
uh okay the line he quotes
is a
what do you call that
um a a cough that won't go away
for years
chronic
chronic cough or something like that you
did you ever have one for like two years
or something I don't know there's
there's chronic things that happen to
you if you're lucky they go away
after a year or two but you just cough
for a year or you coughing to you you go
to the doctor and they say yeah you have
a car and you're like I know I have a
car well that'll be a hundred dollars
and uh
so I just think that won't go away okay
what's the thing that won't go away
chronic chronic
habit of
thinking about what you want
so he he doesn't call it bad habit or
something like that he calls it a
chronic disease
says the chronic disease of
chronic disease of taking care of
yourself first
[Music]
so you being great students
I figure you want the whole four verses
don't listen to Tim okay
you got a picture for me
it's the cover of the three Treasures
prayer book
no yes
anyway it's there
okay don't worry about it let's do them
let's do the four lines
the four verses
on
when he's quoting is the uh
la machupa which you did the first night
here okay it's called the offering to
Lama
that's the first prayer I ever sat in I
I arrived in the Himalayas on a bus
I went to this Tibetan Library
it just opened for foreigners and there
was like 20 monks there doing Loma chip
I walked into llama machopa's first
thing I ever heard
and uh
here's the first verse
chronic disease
of taking care of myself first
if you suddenly wake up and see it's
giving you all the problems you ever had
means Lilian day is a very rare Tibetan
word that means uh
you figure out who's really causing you
trouble what do you call that you put
the blame on the right person but
there's a saying in English
yeah you could say that
something like that I mean you just wake
up you say oh
that oh all these years that's what's
been messing me up you know you're like
you put the blame in the right place
uh the blame okay
and then he says I want you to feel Kun
Kun means uh
cleansing means
what is it when someone hurts you over
and over again and you start getting
resent yeah yeah that's good
means uh
it's funny because here's the Buddhist
teacher saying please feel resentful
you know please feel resentment
for what
he says the dungeon means the great
demon
you carry myself first he said I want
you to feel I want you to develop
resentment
you have been
ruining my life my whole life and I'm
fat I'm so sick of you and now I finally
figured out
there's this sense of Discovery in this
verse ha
Sherlock
you know
that's what's been messing me up my
whole life you know you're like aha I
figured it out you know and then you're
like God you're such an you know
to to give me this trouble my whole life
you know and then you
he's like cursing here like it's not me
okay
uh he's like you should say you
I figured it out you're the one who's
been causing me all this trouble it's
supposed to be a verse of Discovery and
resentment
okay
please best bless me to murder this guy
who
my habit of taking care of myself first
that's the first verse okay
man I'm chasing below
this is zimba okay past tense
taking care of my mom s
okay taking care of my mom's
uh now I figured it out
it's the sweetest thing I can do with my
life it's the most fun sweet thing to do
in my life is just look at what other
people need what other people want help
them get what they want help them get
what they need and that's the sweetest
way to live a human life
uh and it's so satisfying and it's so
sexy and it's so fun okay and he's like
this is also a verse of
Discovery whoa I just figured out what's
really fun
is taking care of other people what they
want you know and doing that first
I'll I'll take care of myself I'll get
there
by the way it's not uh giving up
anything
he's just saying take care of everybody
okay
okay you're you're one of everybody so
don't worry about it we'll cover you you
cover everybody you got yourself covered
okay then
he says something hard
if everybody in the world decided they
hate your guts
like uh
you have the karma to be trolled by
everybody online
okay
so clay chairperson
may you bless me my lover
to
love them even more
more than my own life means my own life
even if I get trolled by the whole world
everyone
please bless me
that I will cherish those trollers
even more than my own life
that's boy not easy
okay
third verse
[Music]
yeah a kid two-year-old we have this
derogatory
connotation in English he's acting like
a
two-year-old
you know
I've never spent time around little kids
because I never had them but
I've been around my dream when he hit
two it it was a little difficult
that's when I kicked him out of the
studio at DCI uh so cheap around the
encounter means uh
in Buddhism is a
two-year-old is an insult
for people who are selfish who take care
of themselves first it's also a synonym
for
someone who has not seen emptiness
directly probably the two are very
connected Can we see
seriously if you don't see emptiness
you're more likely to
take care of yourself first
there's a connection there we got to
talk more about it okay
okay
but Buddhists
they just focus on everything that other
people need
[Music]
may I
come to the realization of the
difference okay yewa means uh
bless me to realize the difference
between a two-year-old and a being who
sees all objects in the universe
[Music]
okay it's like bless me to see the
difference
between a two selfish little
two-year-old
and a Buddha who sees all objects in the
universe you know please bless I don't
know why you need a blessing to see that
but uh please bless me to get the to get
the difference okay and
and with that understanding bless me to
dakshine
bless me to do the practice of
when you say it's two different things
okay never call it exchanging only call
it
equal rights they want to say equalizer
it sounds like a battery to me I I don't
know uh
you know may I
may I come to the understanding that
everybody has an equal right to
happiness
and then may I exchange myself and
others which doesn't mean what you think
it does
and I just decided at this very moment
it's been cooking in my mind Tim
he doesn't go to shantideva
he doesn't do the classic numji
so we better
you know slight detour
uh to get the correct details
okay
all right but that's another story for
later in the week
so please bless me once I figured out
the difference between a two-year-old
and a being who sees every object in the
universe
therefore I should do ducks and yummy
that's weird right got got it
because I understand the difference
between a two-year-old who just focuses
on what they want and two-year-olds do
by the way
except my tree who always feeds people
but bless me to see the difference
between these two people therefore let
me exchange myself and others
what's the logic there why does one
follow from the other
that's something you have to think about
okay
okay last verse
this is uh
this is a very very famous summary
uh from the Llama of these ideas okay
here's the most famous verse summarizing
these ideas
taking care of myself first
was the door to every problem I ever had
in my whole life
every problem I've ever had in my whole
life
sooner or later
it can be traced back to trying to take
care of myself first
what's the next verse going to say
yeah that the opposite she
taking care of others
is the foundation of all good quality
qualities by the way he's making a pun
Buddhist pun here
writing in the 1600s I think
I think first tension llama
and he says he
source of all my good
okay he says the source of all my good
is thinking of my mother's birth you
know and he's making up time because
that's the famous
poem by Jason Kaba we're working on a
new version of that book by the way
so that was called preparing for tundra
and change it to daughter the diamond
way or something like that okay
uh danger ducks and Jamie Nelson now I'm
learning about
therefore let me study yoga
okay now George nowador here is Yoga
it's the Tibetan word for yoga
Jorah is obvious because that means to
join like huge the Sanskrit root huge
join oxens on a yoke
or or yoga practice right but here he
says uh
now
now I mean now Jor is the Tibetan
translation of yoga the Sanskrit word
yoga Jorah is easy it means to connect
but now means accurately
so the word for
uh
the word for yoga in tibetan is accurate
practice
create app
of myself to my practice how's that
that's the two then word for yoga
I stay yoga here
exchanging myself and others so
what did he leave out there
yum
we finished with the equal thing
let's go to the dark scene number let's
sorry
so by the way you can say dark Shan
yamje is
it's two different practices
is two different practices
recognize equal right to happiness and
then exchange what I want with others
what others want okay like that two
different practices you can't do the
jail without the number
you can't
exchange yourself and others without
recognizing that they have rights also
okay cool
yeah
please bless me to make this
please bless me to be smart enough to
make this my main practice
okay it's very beautiful line the last
line is very beautiful please bless me
to be smart enough spiritually
to make it my main practice
to take care of what other people want
and by the way just as a as a way of
life
it's very very satisfying
look it's a very very uh enjoyable when
you get good at it
uh just watching what other people want
what other people need
it's a very sweet lie it's a very very
cool nice way to live it's you you feel
good all day long
okay it's a great
it's a great it's no sacrifice it's a
pleasure
all right
next picture you guys got pictures for
me
yeah I was trying to find a picture of
exchanging and that's the best I could
come up with
I don't know you could read something to
the square I don't know
uh okay
uh this is a Tibetan word called
four
Cosa
Cosa means uh the position that you
occupy
so
in an election
uh cosine means a position like a
political position
like a presidency or a
to be a senator or something is a Cosa
and
that's the classic meaning
you know
like chipor
die and
move on boy
move on to your next one okay here it
means
switch you and the other person okay
switch
switch positions how's that
exchange positions
okay and the exchange is very important
in this section of the alarm room learn
to exchange positions
he's gonna say uh in the next paragraph
it's like for the first time if you uh
go up to the Dome here it's a beautiful
walk by the way
go from the Llama house up to the Dome
and see if you can catch Tim in his
underwear or something uh but uh no I
mean I never look in the window I just
go up to the Dome and there's about
there's a sweet balcony there you can
oversee the whole valley
and you can see across about the same
elevation
is a little tiny common up on the end
here up way high
I don't know if you've ever been in
there it's got a compost toilet that's
very similar to a Volkswagen
like to get on top of it you gotta do
yoga
uh
I I lived I lived there I mean I I had
they built it for me
and I stayed there one night and and I
never been back uh but uh
they're on the same elevation and uh
it's one thing to go up on the Dome and
look at that little cabin
and straight across and then the retreat
values like that but then
if you
climb down from the Dome and walk down
and then climb up to the little cabin
and forget these numbers I hate these
numbers like I said where are you
staying cabin 13. and my last week that
was cabin eight and in my time it was
cabin four
and I'm like
I get anyway
climb up there and look at the Dome
you see what I mean
and that's what he he says if you want
to know what dox and yamji feels like
go up to the Dome stand there enjoy The
View
and then go down walk across the valley
walk up to this other Mountain at the
same height and look back at the Dome
and that's what Dakshin MJ feels like
that's what exchanging yourself with
other feels like any
he says if you want the feeling of it
do it a couple times to pick two
mountains
not too high okay
and uh
go walk to the other one and look back
at the first one and you'll get the
feeling that that's how it's supposed to
feel when you do dachshund so you're
looking back at yourself okay
and we'll talk more about it it's a
it's a little bit
weird okay
changing self and others
doesn't refer to
uh
doesn't refer to you pretend to be
guessing Michael or something like that
it doesn't mean that he says he makes a
point about it he says it doesn't mean
you try to pretend to be guessing
doesn't mean that
but what you have to exchange is the
is the feeling of who you're supposed to
take care of
you're not exchanging yourself and
others
you're exchanging the feeling of who
you're supposed to take care of with the
old feeling of who you're supposed to
take care of got it
you're not supposed to switch out
your hair for my hair
because you don't want to do that
uh what you want to do is switch out
your feeling about who's who you should
be taking care of
that's all
it doesn't mean you try to pretend to
look like guessing Michael or something
like that
it means you switch out
your feeling of who you should take
who's priority
who gets priority when you're deciding
who to take care of okay
okay what's the priorities you don't
switch to people
okay all right go support action
dog Center Min means I'm not saying you
should pretend to be Rob and Rob
pretends to be you I'm not saying that
no wrong temper somebody
in the old days he used to China focus
on what you wanted and then you kind of
have paid attention to what other people
wanted but it was secondary
so it's not like you ignored people
completely
but it was secondary it it was a good
thing to do after you took care of
yourself
he says you are now you have to switch
that attitude up and
dance
flip it gosan dope means flip it wrong
temper
what you want to exchange is who you're
taking care of first
okay uh that's that's exchanging self
another okay
it's changing attitudes and not
exchanging identities
cool you're not supposed to look like
you don't want to look like this all
right
foreign
now he says something difficult
and I want you to think about it today
in your in your retreat
while you're doing Retreat okay while
you're in your cabin
off your phone give your phone a rest
you don't need a rest from the internet
your phone needs a rest from the
internet
okay so respect your phone
before you respect yourself take care of
your phone he's tired he's exchanging
electrons relentlessly
seven average 7.5 hours a day
give him a let him take a rest okay
okay
[Music]
try this is a hard instruction okay
listen and tell me what you think okay
and and I'm open to
I'm not sure about this line
I'm not sure if I accept it okay
what you think or tell me how you think
we should read it
read it Jack
uh he says
in days gone by
I would take care of myself
first
and if others had to slide I let it
happen
like I took care of myself for sure
first
and then then second I would take care
of other people but if
and if I didn't really have time to take
care of them as well as I took care of
myself it was okay
if what do you call that if if their
needs kind of
slighted
you know if if I didn't quite get done
what they needed done I was okay as long
as I got done when I needed done
then it's not like I ignored them
completely okay like I was worried about
other people's welfare but if it wasn't
done with quite the enthusiasm that my
own welfare was done with
disco is okay you know okay got it
that's called yellow
um
he says now I want you to do that to
yourself
okay so by the time you sleep at the end
of the day I want you to make sure that
what other people needed got done
and what you needed Maybe
didn't get done Tim says I should slow
down from the translators you know if
the translator just could learn to read
my mind and
and translate it before I said it
went
and work towards that
um okay
no I'm kidding
so I I'm not sure I buy this I'll say it
again and then I want to hear your
opinion okay
[Music]
my day
you took care of the most important
stuff for you
and then oftentimes that didn't leave
enough time
to take care of what other people needed
as well as
what you knew
or to finish them as completely as you
did what you needed okay
now he says now he has a proposal
let your own stuff slide
and by the end of the day
make sure you have taken care of what
other people need
I'm not sure I'd buy it
what do you think
Angela
talk loud
don't don't do this let other people
unslide
you have to talk go ahead
talk loud
um
you've taught us in the past that
way back
that if you're gonna be a good mother to
children you have to take care of Mom
Mom has to take care of Mom a little bit
in order to be able to take care of the
kids so I I don't know I like that
feeling about that it's important you
know otherwise if Mother slides then
they can't take care of everyone for the
kids I guess yeah
I that's kind of what I feel but anyone
but don't do this there's self another
thing
I was gonna say it might be that
by taking care of everyone else
throughout the day when you come to the
end of the day you may find that your
own needs have already been taken care
of say say the last part again
by the time you get to the end of the
day after taking care of everyone you
may find that what you need is already
taken care of in the process okay I like
I'll buy that one
[Music]
Tim had one
you need a box I think the
because you said yesterday you talked
about the 50 50.
where we don't necessarily
we do want to pay attention
but I think here he's saying because
we've had such a terrible habit of
taking care of ourselves maybe swinging
to the other side first
would be a good practice to then be able
to come back to the
middle yeah I I also I I was thinking
that yesterday we have to overcompensate
because we've been biased towards
ourselves for so long that what feels
like over compensation is probably
halfway
yeah I like that one too
anybody else
Jim I just wanted to comment on that
I've seen students who seem to swing
drastically to
caring for others and then what happens
is they have a breakdown yeah yeah and
they can no longer care for others so
there's got to be this I think the 50 50
balance there's got to be a balance in
there
well I was just thinking about what you
said yesterday about having the ability
to bend time and space
so ultimately you have to be able to do
both I think
okay
um
Joe please
I'd say do it for a couple of months and
see how it turns out
[Applause]
other people need to plant seeds and
someone we need to be there so that
someone can plant
their caring seeds in us so that's why
we help other people and if we do it all
ourselves if we plan our life ourselves
take care of ourselves we don't leave
space for others to take care of us so
we don't help them yeah okay cool yeah
thank you
um because until now I have not seen
have not seen the direct perception of
the emptiness this means that I still
have the fake buddhistava
and I think I must like myself until I
see The Emptiness directly because that
is the time I got the true buddhisattva
and that is the time I can jump into all
the words and love them ultimately
and that is why I must take care of
myself until I'm become a Buddha because
when I was a Buddha uh all my words
can enjoy the protection of a Buddha
Paradise
I was in a position last night to make
the choice of take care of somebody else
or take care of my needs to finish the
day and I I realized oh my God what a
wonderful opportunity to learn how to
manage these choices a little
differently so that I can you know help
both them and myself I was moving
furniture it was late my friend needed
tax advice on the phone so I said while
you are looking for the tax line you
have the question on I'm going to push
this heavy thing
Translate
and then I'll push the cabinet while
you're looking for the tax line tell me
when you find it I'll stop pushing the
chest and answer the question so it was
a wonderful opportunity to figure out
different management
approaches
to taking care of both of us at the end
of the day
enough
good
you're kind of doing both right
on the point of that vulnerable girls
said about balance
when you want to do something for
yourself first do something for somebody
else
50 50 before you do something you do
something for another person okay cool
that's cool
uh uh one last thing
[Music]
um
so my proposal okay and just something I
I was teaching in Japan
at our new University there's an MBA
program so we were having some of the
first classes and they asked me to teach
in a there's a course called uh
Innovation and Entrepreneurship
and so I was supposed to teach one of
those classes along with a western
professor
and it's it's a sweet uh
it's a sweet University because I have
to teach classes with Western professors
and um
and it's actually working out really
cool because they come with their big
thick book about Innovation and
some of them have never been in business
you know what I mean so anyway
uh but uh it forced me to think about
Innovation and then I was uh I I chose
some of the Innovations I made in the
diamond business and and one of the
reasons we succeeded
among I think there's ten thousand
Diamond companies
the reason we were number one
I think was that we had all these
Innovations we had very weird
Innovations some of which are still
Secret
uh of how to process diamonds and how to
make jewelry and you know
and I was thinking about those
Innovations and they were all done
during retreat
all of them you know and ACI all started
in one of those retreats
so the Innovations in my life
which which made the company the the
largest in the world for Diamond Jewelry
uh and Warren Buffett bought it in 2009
um what
what made those Innovations was certain
kinds of Retreats done here and other
places
at Diamond Mountain so I we were talking
Tim and I were talking about
um
and son-in-law about doing an innovation
Retreat here maybe
of training people
to be innovative
through Retreat how to use Retreat time
to be Innovative even just in your
business life but you can also use it
for your family challenges right so I
think this idea of when you have a
problem
or when you have a challenge
to to solve it by going into retreat
it's kind of cool and I've been watching
this Christian TV show
uh The Chosen right
that seems to be what Jesus did whenever
he had a big challenge he saw all his
disciples say go away
there's I love it they say where you
where are you going he says you don't
need to know and and he says I'll be
back and they say rare and he says you
don't need to know
you know they said they're saying like
what city are you gonna come back to he
says you don't need to know
we'll find out you know and uh so his
reaction
to a problem
is to go into a retreat you know and
then uh
and then to think of some Innovative
solution
in Retreat and I think to have a
like a course where you teach people
how to be innovative
by doing retreat
um how to do an innovation Retreat I
think it'd be something that we're going
to try out here
right
uh so we'll we'll let you know more why
am I saying that why am I saying that
you tell me why am I saying that
yeah be Innovative in pleasing both
yourself and others okay find
super
innovative solutions
to get everything you want done
and take care of everyone else what they
need done
at the same time
and to me
that's one of the greatest skills you
can learn in a human life
you know and I I'm saying it from age 70
right
It's a Wonderful skill to have
to find
Solutions
to other people's needs and your needs
to find this Grand Solutions
that that
give to other people exactly what they
need and they give you exactly what you
need at the same time
and in in my opinion if you can learn
that skill
your whole life is really fun
extremely fun
to learn that skill
that kind of innovation where you
you'd make a decision that other getting
other people what they need is now
priority
getting getting other people what they
need is now priority in my life but
it's also important for me to get some
stuff that I want
you know and it's a lot more fun to come
up with Solutions
that make both happen at the same time
and and I think you can learn to do that
I think you can be trained to do that
and I think it'd be fun to have a
retreat based
just to have a special Retreat of
I would call an innovation Retreat or
something where creativity retreat
and I think it would be a beautiful
skill
to teach people so we're talking with
diamond mountain and ACI to do it here
some kind of innovation Retreat like how
to be innovative
about how you satisfy what you want and
what everyone else wants at the same
time
in some kind of grand
solution that gives both parties more
than they
wanted they asked me to teach a
different course there which is
negotiation
and it's a similar uh skill
you know a real successful business
negotiator
comes up with solutions that favor both
parties
and they create advantages for both
and that's that's real negotiation and
somebody wrote a book in United States
called The Art of a deal or something
like that
the whole the whole
premise was that you should get what you
want and they shouldn't get what they
want
and to me that's the most idiotic thing
I ever heard of uh you know real
negotiation should be
Mutual
what do you call it
both parties get more than what they
expected when they got into the deal
both parties should get much more than
they wanted when they started
negotiating that's that's a negotiation
so I was thinking we could do this
business
we could do business Retreats here and
it'd be fun because it's all we're
writing new books on these subjects for
the University I'm writing new books for
the university for this
for these they funded
uh I think it'd be fun for ACI and
and diamond mountain
to have Retreats just with that theme
like negotiation or or
how to
how to get both parties more than what
they want okay like
I think a big
cool innovation
to be innovate truly innovative
and in my business life
why why that company we went from three
people to ten thousand people
we doubled every 18 months for 19 years
we hired
equals if we have 500 staff we hire 500
staff within six months it's incredible
and I think it was uh the retreats
it was the Retreats the the
that did it okay so I think
I don't know Retreat something like
Mutual benefit negotiation training
Retreat all right uh
if you get used to it he says you can
learn to do the exchange right if you
get used to it
for example if you go stand on one
mountain and then run over to the other
mountain and look back at the mountain
you are standing on I'm going to fast
too
that's where he says he gives the
mountain suggestion okay
all right uh we got five minutes my
teacher taught me never to waste five
minutes
Napa what's Napa
what's what is fun
land he says let's go to we have five
minutes I'm gonna start Shanti deva's
version of Dakshin yummy okay
and it's not in the long room and I
don't care
uh but here it is maybe I can finish it
uh
and then I want you to want you to try
it today in your meditation okay
and uh
this is how it no it's too much to tell
you and I'll tell you the first part
today and I'll tell you the rest
tomorrow okay
so if it's me
I would start with
someone on your own level like at work
okay so someone who's a colleague not
your boss
and not your employee
someone who's on the same level as you
okay okay so it's a co-worker or a
colleague in your whatever your job is
it's your colleague okay they are not
your Superior
and they don't report to you
they are you're coming
and then being colleagues in an
organization
implies
the possibility for jealousy
or competitiveness okay it's Human
Nature
when you're at the same level as another
person
there's a tendency towards
competitiveness okay
which then uh implies and here's the
nasty part
when you
start with competitiveness
where you go to
is the wish that the other person should
fail
and uh jealousy
or competitiveness
evolves
desire that the other person should
if you're competing
with your colleague at work to see who
can make the most sales for the month
and they suddenly break their leg and
can't sell anything for a couple weeks
there's this kind of
sick pleasure you know there's this kind
of sick
feeling then oh gee I'm so sorry you
broke your leg
and uh
okay so so competitiveness
between equals that's the natural state
of people uh
now here's what's the real
exchange of self and others okay here's
the real one ready
yes you put yourself in their shoes that
parts that part's correct
that you do the first part of this
practice
the first half of this practice
is what you think it is when you hear
exchange self in others okay yes you do
put yourself in their shoes okay
so
that part what you always thought was
exchanging self in others
correct the first half is correct you do
put yourself
in English in American English we say
put yourself in the other person's shoes
it means uh
think of how they feel
okay is and that's that's
only the first half of exchanging stuff
notice okay got it
can anybody guess what the second half
is
and that's what we haven't that's what
he doesn't talk about in The Long room
look at yourself then yeah yeah
exactly and that's what he doesn't make
clear in the long Rim Shanti Deva says
it's not enough
to try to think how they're feeling it's
not enough
he says put yourself in their shoes and
look back at your throat
and see how it feels when someone else
is praying that you will break your leg
and not make the sales this month
you know see how bad that feels
and it's a very depressing meditation if
you don't get depressed from exchanging
self and others you're not doing it
right
okay is to look back at you
that's the important part okay Shanti
Davis says it's not enough to just try
to imagine how cat's feeling right now
and probably her bottom sore maybe you
should end on time
that's not enough
you have to sit
in cat's body looks your cat's eyes at
gushing Michael
you know
bombasting on past the end time when
everyone's butt is sore
doesn't he get it doesn't he see how we
feel what's wrong with him you know and
that's where you're supposed to go with
Dachshund okay that's traditional okay
okay and now uh
I'm gonna give you homework okay
Shanti Deva takes it one more step okay
a
exchange yourself in others yes okay try
to understand cat's bottom might be sore
right now
okay
step two
look back at yourself through Cat's eyes
and see how she feels about you
when you're not when you're abusing the
time
okay
and then here's the one I want you to
work on and I'd like to hear your
results tomorrow okay got it here's your
assignment okay
do it for three levels
exchange with someone who's
higher than you in authority
like Sonu
like the boss of diamond mountain like
exchange yourself with the boss
and then exchange yourself with someone
who's at your own level
and then exchange yourself with
yeah someone who's working for you on
the food chain
they report to you
anybody reporting to you there's lots of
what do you call foxes
javelinas
you know how how does it feel to work
for you
okay that's a great one if you're a boss
of anybody
how does it feel to work for you
how how does it feel how does it feel to
look against you Michael when you look
for Christian when you work for gushing
Michael
how how does it what do they think when
they look at you
and and that's the real shantadavian
thing okay exchange yourself and others
at three levels and see how it feels and
I I want to know tomorrow
what you come up with okay
watch you come up uh what are the main
emotional themes
of working for you
okay what are the main emotional themes
of being your colleague
and what are the main emotional themes
of being your boss
okay how does it feel
okay cool tomorrow that's your homework
that's your meditation I suggest you do
it on different meditations
don't try to do all three in one sitting
do three sittings okay
so three sittings I don't care how long
ten minutes
20 minutes okay three sittings before
tomorrow
somebody who's your boss somebody who's
you you're calling and someone who works
for you okay got it cool
all right Timothy
anything any announcements don't forget
your free ebooks
and
if you get excited about the free ones
maybe you wanna
buy some of the the better ones
just kidding